hello and welcome it is October 30th
2023 we're here in active inference
guest stream number
62.1 with Michael Carl and friends today
the talk is called Deep temporal models
of the translation process a translation
agent grounded in empirical data we're
going to have a press presentation by
Michael followed by a panel discussion
so if you're watching live please feel
free to write any questions in the live
chat otherwise we're looking forward to
this presentation and discussion so
thank you again for joining Michael and
friends to you for the
presentation yeah good morning so I talk
deep temporal models in the of the
translation process I would like to
outline an idea for an architecture for
the translation process um and uh to do
this um I have three points here first I
would like to introduce the translation
process research what this is and the
data that we have collected I will show
the data acquisition tools uh visual
visualization and segmentation then I
will come into an architecture uh that
is based on these uh partial Observer
remark of decision processes and that
uses the free energy principle and in
the end I will talk about an
experimental implementation and uh and
initialization of those
parameters okay before starting talking
about translation process research here
is a uh is a small um contextualization
of this uh of this field of research so
it started around 40 years ago and it's
all about uh investigating what happens
in the mind of the translator so how do
translators uh produce translation how
do they have how is it possible to have
two languages in one mind what makes
translations difficult and so on so this
type of research started around 40 years
ago with um with crings uh around the
beginning of the 80s and they were using
introspection and thinkaloud protocols
that was an laborsome manual analysis
that went along with this then 10 years
later about uh Aunt l yakobson deviced
the key logging tool called translog
that would record
keystrokes translator would sit in front
of an editor and type in the
translations and the keystrokes would be
locked then um 10 years later in 2005 it
tracking devices were added to this
device so with an it trer um The Gaze on
the screen would be recorded in time and
with a key loger the output so we have
an it trer uh recording where on the
screen a trans dat looks and the key log
inut log where what the translator
writes and so we have somehow an input
and an output and then in 2010 around
that time I started collecting all these
data into a
database putting the data that we had
collected by then in
one one database and a couple of years
ago we started having this with a
browser user interface and Python and R
interface and so I like to call this
translation data analytics because it
resembles a little bit data analytics so
we have these these python tools and the
large database that I will talk later a
little bit about and so this um our
research
is um on behavioral measures means there
keystrokes and gase data but there's of
course also other kinds of uh data
acquisition like brain activities EEG
fmri and so on but I will talk about
this part where we have um key key
logging data uh and ey
tracking okay so how does it work so
this is a screen uh this is a picture of
the kind of setup that we have used
quite frequently in this research you
see here on the screen translog 2 that
uh is an editor so in on the top of this
window here you have a source text
window that translator is supposed to
translate translate in the lower editing
uh box here and while typing there the
keystrokes would be logged in time so
every keystroke comes with a time stamp
and one could then look into the Rhythm
and when in the rhythm of translations
when does the translator time fluently
and so on when do they pause and then in
addition we we have here an eye trer we
have light bulbs here this light is
reflected in the eyes of a
translator uh and there is a device a
camera 2 here which then would record
and calculate where on the screen the
translator is looking and so we have the
two things we have the input to the
translator so the basically the the data
um that goes into the translator's mind
and the keystrokes that come out and
this data can be then processed um and
the uh and and represented in several
ways and one way of representing this is
shown here so this is a translation
progression graph where we have uh on
the y axis here on the left side we have
the source text that consists of 160
words it's an English Source text and
that is translated into a target
language and then on the x axis
horizontally we have the uh translation
process data and then first we see here
that the translator quite uh tightly
quite nicely reads the entire Source
text the blue AES here are fixations on
the source text you can see how the
translator reads the source text it's
the orientation phase then we have here
drafting phase where the translator
basically drafts types in the
translation and the green dots are then
fixations on the target side so the blue
dots are the fixations on the source
text the green dots are fixations on the
target side you can see how the
translator goes back and forth between
the source and the target side and then
behind here you have black dots and red
dots are the insertions are black red
are deletion so we can trace how the
translation evolves this would be the
drafting phase and then in the end we
have a revision phase where again the
translator reads in this case almost the
entire text mostly with the eyes on the
target side so we see many Green Dots
pluses in this case here so this is one
translation style where we have nicely
these three faces but other translators
behave quite differently so for instance
this translator here uh as you can see
here reads a little bit one and a half
segment and then starts typing in the
translation then again here in segment
three reads this segment here the source
segment and then types in and then goes
on quite fluently with only very little
look ahead in the source text
immediately reads and types out the
translation with no larger orientation
phase and also no revision whatsoever it
seems so if we zoom into this part here
of this process it looks like this again
we can see on the left side here the
source text English Source text and on
the right side a translation into
Spanish in this case and you can see
here that all these words are aligned so
the source English Source words and the
Spanish Target words are aligned on a
small level here we for instance we can
see that there is two words in the
Spanish side aligned to three words on
the
source uh on the source side so we see
on the here on the horizontal axis we
see the word alignments between the
source and the target text and again on
the uh uh here in the graph the
translation um data so the process data
so first uh in the first couple of
seconds the blue dots uh signal or
indicate a reading on the source side
Source text trunk so we can see that the
translator takes in some new information
from the source side here from The
Source text and then types out here a
translation with the eyes on the target
side reading here these words then
something happens in you can see there
was something typed an O and deletion of
an O and so on so there seems to be some
kind of typos a little bit of problem
and then In This Moment the translator
then moves with their eyes from The
Source text to the Target text
presumably to check what happens on the
screen here and then goes on smoothly
typing here again something seems to H
happen but it looks like something
different a little bit because maybe um
the translator has an intuition that
something went wrong here so we see this
three fixations on uh on the target side
L normas okay around here and this whole
stretch and then there is a deletion and
once this deletion uh is uh somehow
these translation hurdle or kind of a
small problem is solved the translator
goes on
smoothly okay so so we have two kinds of
streams here we have a stream of
keystrokes the translator types in
translat ation and we have a stream of
gaze data where the translator reads
stuff and these two streams are
synchronized as you can see on this
slide here but they can be also
fragmented segmented in different ways
and one way of fragmenting the stream
into units into uh yeah into into units
of translation units here in this case
is by looking into the pause so here we
can see there is a pause a keystroke
pause no keystrokes occurred for more
than one second this is the white
stretch here and then in Black uh these
black strip boxes here would indicate
coherent typing so no keystroke is um no
keystroke Gap more than one second so
it's kind of coherent typing and we see
that there's pausing and typing pausing
and typing which is an observation uh
for all kinds of text production that
text production occurs in in form of
pausing and typing and it's assumed that
in the pausing in the paes the
translators or the writers take in some
new information or think about a kind of
a problem or something and then they you
have these bursts these typing bursts in
which the text is produced and the
sequence of this pauses and typing would
be a translation unit and Fabi alare
here in this panel has uh started
looking into those a couple of years ago
with some interesting results so you can
see so this there's here in this case
there's not only a sequence of pausing
and typing but also we have here the
Gaze going from the source to the Target
to the source to the Target and this
looks like quite independently while the
guys move from the source to the Target
and so on the eyes the hands type out
stuff or not so we can then chop up this
kind of data also in smaller units
depending on the coordination of the I
and the hands and here we have called
this translation units sorry activity
units where we can see here a unit or a
stretch of time where the eyes are on
the source text only here we can see a
stretch of time where uh the eyes are on
the target side activity unit of type
two and then we see here different uh
units where the eyes go back and forth
between the source uh and the targets
side of the window of the of the of the
screen while typing so we have activity
unit five is T typing while reading the
source text six is typing while reading
the target text so you can see that the
I go back and forth between the source
and the target while typing or while uh
while reading with no typing so this is
one way of U chopping up the activ uh
the the translation process data and
recently we have also started um
annotating what we call higher level
translation States so the assumption is
that the translator be can be in a in a
phase of orientation so translator can
take in information and
orientation or they can be in a in a
state of flow in a flow state in a in a
state of fluent production where uh the
text is produced or uh just like here
that there can be hesitation so some
surprising things pop up some some
intuition is something went wrong and uh
and they they come into a a state of
hesitation where until until the hurdle
uh is solved and then they go on with uh
again of fluent fluent translation or an
orientation so this was a kind of an
annotation that we uh had previously but
before now going into uh the uh the
modeling in uh in terms of an
hierarchical architecture I would like
to uh show how we uh have already
annotated or analyzed this data
previously here you can see that we
looked into these activity units means
these uh types of uh units and we can
make a distinction between reading a
translator can read The Source text the
translator can read the target text
translator can
write
while can write or they can pause so
where there is no input and it's a
completely connected graph as you can
see where a translator can switch from
any one state to another so means we can
we can look then into byrams of these uh
activity units here to figure out what
kind of typical situations we can see
and some time ago a couple of people uh
did this kind of research so looking
into diagrams of activity units and then
see what other the typical transitions
uh between these activity units and we
figured out that expert translators for
instance move more frequently from The
Source text reading to typing so they
cycle around this uh way where when the
text becomes more difficult we can see
that there is reading and Source text
reading and Target text reading there we
see some somehow slightly more Cycles
around this way and then in post editing
uh the eyes are more often on the target
side and writing so we can see cycling
the translator cycling around this way
okay so this was one type of analysis uh
that has been conducted but as you can
see all this is um on one level so this
is just a flat kind of a Bagram
architecture assumption uh there were
other ideas of that there is a probably
multiple concurrent uh processes going
on in the translator's mind and this is
the monitor model that uh we suggested
like around 10 years ago moit and I and
others too and here uh the idea is that
we have two different kinds of processes
one horizontal process in which a
translator engages in kind of
automatized routines um
U uh by producing a translation and
these while producing these translations
a monitor would uh loom in the
background and the in the back of the
mind and check whether the produced
translation works out whether this is in
in line according to the goals to the to
the translation goals and to the
requirements of the translation and if
something goes wrong the monitor would
interfere and stop this uh kind of
horizontal processes and um and
interfere with remedies or with with a
changing uh changing the output so the
monitor model but is not the only model
that has suggested this kind of
architecture there's actually quite a
few similar suggestions here is one from
Anthony PIM in
2017 he talks about a cruise mode and a
bump mode and then he says the cruise
mode is the default mode that's where
the translator usually wants to be in a
cruise mode in a in a flow State and
then until they will stay there in this
flow mode or Cruise mode until something
goes wrong a bump occurs and then uh the
translator U is pushed into this bump
mode which requires some attention and
He suggests that there is a couple of
strategies how a translator come can
come out of this bump mode back into to
a cruise mode and he said he has several
suggestions from simple to more complex
here low effort to high effort and then
the translator interferes more or less
in uh in the in the output in the in the
Target text and here he has a couple of
strategies how to do
this there were other suggestions
already from 87 the this kic talk about
uh atoc mode uh atoc block and rest
block are good about S Mode and IM mode
but there's a so you can see there's a
couple of similar ideas people named
this slightly
differently so before going now into the
um uh architecture I still want to talk
a little bit um about the uh translation
process
database which we have used uh in our
study so the translation process
database is an effort as I said before
that started around uh 20 2010 so 13
years ago or so and um it has lots of
data from different studies uh
translation uh PhD projects and similar
studies so more than 90 studies are
collected there there's more than 6,000
translation
sessions with mostly uh they all have
key loged data so all these translation
sessions are logged with keystrokes in
different not only in translog 2 but
there's different kinds of data
acquisition uh tools
and mostly they have also ey tracking
data so all these data together makes up
several hundreds hours of process data
there is very many different translators
and we have different uh translations
into 10 more than 10 different languages
mostly this is from English English into
all these different languages that you
can see here and in different kinds of
modes also mostly from scratch
translation but very much also post
editing machine translation post editing
that's a situation where the translator
instead of producing a text from scratch
already has a
pre-translated output from a machine
translation system and then posts May
means takes out the errors and so on so
but we also have a spoken translation
interpreting side translation and
dictation so this is the inter contents
of the database and this database is
publicly available it can be downloaded
from Source Forge
um free of charge and all this data all
these more than 6,000 sessions are
aligned on a segment and a Word level
and we have extracted features from this
data uh that is represented in 11 tables
I wouldn't talk about this here um with
more than 300 features so a very rich
database publicly available but uh if
researchers are interested they can also
have a private account with a browser
interface uh they can upload their own
data and then we have an an interface to
Jupiter with r and also python ex and uh
and and some some toolkits to uh extract
the data all this data from the public
part and from from their private um uh
data and integrate this and we have a
toolkit to work with this data now I
would like to come back to this data
that we have annotated here so we have
these three phes okay orientation Flow
State and hesitation and we have in an
experiment uh uh annotated six texts
with these three states and we had two
annotators t and Y they annotated both
these six texts so six texts each text
about 150 words so this is almost around
a thousand words or so and um these six
texts consist Ed of
1,815 activity units of type one to 8 so
we have six types six different types of
activity units T1 is reading on the
source text t22 is reading on the target
text this is typing only typing with
eyes on the source text on the target
text and this is paing so we have a
total of this
1,815 activity units and they were
annotated uh with the s o and S labels
from these two annotators and you can
see here that mostly in the um s state
so in this Flow State we have one of
those states that go along with typing
so T4 T5 T6 whereas in this hesitation
phase we have mostly
42 per chance um that we we see the ice
on the source or the target side where
else the orientation phase is a little
bit undecided here then we also checked
um the um how well these two annotators
uh coordinate how well is the how how
good is the translator inter
interannotator agreement and they agreed
best in the Flow State eight uh so you
can see here uh that the interannotator
agreement is best uh in this fluent
translation that was the most easy to
detect and Le least control verial and
according to this chart here they um
were most confused where this
orientation
phase uh which then
sometimes the other translator would
consider this to be an s or an H
State okay so this part then about the
data and I would like now to talk about
how we manag to get this into um uh into
this uh uh architecture and first a word
about this free energy principle and um
um what that could mean for a
translator here is this picture shows
that there's a translator uh working on
a text and then we have this text in the
environment and the idea of this free
energy principle is that a translator
comes into a
situation with some expectations so a
translator usually is told what this
text is about what is the target Lang
anguage what is the the topics or the
the domain of the text and so on so they
come with some kind of expectations a
distribution of predictions and then
they come and observe have some obser
observations and there can be a
discrepancy there can be uh larger or
smaller gap between the observations and
the
predictions and uh then there are two
ways to reduce this free energy so the
amount of discrepancy between this uh
this expectations and the observations
is free energy and this uh is supposed
to be uh or should be minimized this
discrepancy and one way to do this is to
interfere with the text a translator can
interfere with a text so they can
produce a translation there according to
their preferences thereby changing the
environment and then observe something
that they expected and uh and they can
then also change or and or they can
change their internal model right which
would then change the predictions and
ideally a translator would be in a
situation where they have some
predictions H then some actions that uh
goes along with their preferences then
they observe something that they have
predicted they go along the minimally
change uh them the beliefs again and
they would be in a flow State going like
this
smoothly predicting continuations of the
translation and observing that it was
also correct their predictions this can
be formalized in the free energy
principle with the free energy Principle
as follows so we have this Q is the
distribution of the predictions the p is
the distributions of the observations
and if these two distributions are
identical these Divergence would be zero
which um would mean that that yeah so
that the two distributions are identical
and the other part is the evidence which
is a translator produces something
there's an action this Alpha here okay
and if um a translator would try to uh
maximize the probability that an
observation of a of a translation is uh
in in increases right with in the given
context of the Source text so this would
be the evidence so a translator would
would try to maximize this evidence or
to minimize this Divergence in order to
arrive uh into a state into a flow state
or to maintain this Flow
State okay how can this now be modeled
in uh in an architecture so I would like
now to go through these three um States
here through in a drafting phase so I'm
talking about a drafting phase we have
the orientation a flow State and a
hesitation I would like to go and and
look into how this could be modeled in
this paral observable hierarchical model
and so here we can um model this or uh
assume that there is a kind of a markof
process here we have an
observation then a transition into a
successive Flow State then a transition
into a hesitation uh into a state of
hesitation
here and um in this orientation phase a
translator would read a piece of source
text and by reading this they would
allocate some internal resources they
would think about what uh how the
translation could be they would have an
idea whether uh things whether they
first should look up some resources some
words and a lexicon also they would read
in a chunk of source text get a gist of
it how to translate it and in initialize
some kind of internal resources that I
will look to in in a moment and then uh
execute and then be in this Flow State
and execute or produce this translations
more or less fluently while doing this a
monitor process would run in the
background and whenever something goes
wrong or is uh they have the intuition
that something should be different the
monitor Pro process would stop this flow
uh this fluent translation and kick the
translator out into another state in
this case here in the hesitation phase
again we have an initialization of the
resources and so on so we have on this
level one kind of a Markov process and
if we zoom into this part here then um
we can see that the so according to this
uh to to this partial observ Markov
decision processes we have these four
resources the ABCD matrices and the
translator would then initialize those
matrices check first check the
translation whether there's a
translation hurdle here in the
observation then initialize somehow
translation equivalences and these um
matrices here okay how would that work
if you look again into this part so a
translator comes out of this orientation
phase and goes into this state of fluent
translation here we can see again that
the translator reads uh or types in the
translation while reading while the eyes
stay at the places where they type here
in this case on the sour side then goes
to the Target side and so on so if you
look into this uh we have here a small
segment uh the breakdown of a
traditional Norms in English Okay so the
the breakdown of traditional Norms which
is translated into Spanish
and you can see that the typing in of
the translation is in the order of the
Spanish um word order so they would so
they would uh uh translate uh in the
Spanish word order while going with the
eyes back and forth to try find
resources what uh is the next word to be
translated okay um so how how could that
be uh um formalized in this for
formalism again we can uh we can think
of this as a transition of alignment
groups so the translator has initialized
these alignment groups and then in the
order of the target language syntax so
in the order of the French uh final out
outcome okay and
then they uh there would be
initializations of these
um transition
matrices and the likelihood of uh
recognition of the observations and so
on so this would be an
initialization of uh these process but
in addition we have active inference uh
that um that predicts
um the sequence in the future so if a
translator is at a certain stage here in
alignment group two for instance to to
to to produce a translation for this
alignment group the idea of this active
inference is that for at each
moment there would be a possible path
there is a possible path in the future
and uh and and the translator would then
compute what is the best the most likely
or the most effective path to proceed so
what are the transitions uh in the in
the future um and this is called the
expected free energy that is computed
here based on a set of
preferences and uh so basically if you
put this together I will come back to
this a little bit later when I talk
about the initialization of these
matrices here but to have an overview
here so we have here uh on this level we
have these alignment groups and
transitions uh from one alignment group
uh to the next one here and on this
level here we have this active inference
part where kinds of best path is
computed based on
preferences and if you plug this part
into our previous architecture it could
look like this where we have again here
uh allocation of resources or uh so the
the checking whether the alignment
groups how these alignment groups could
be uh initialized then we have here
initialization of these matrices and a
kind of a of a fluent state
in which a
translator um goes over uh produces the
translation um while monitoring what
comes uh whether they are in a good
shape here okay we can see that there
are two levels one level here a state
level and another level an activity an
activity level where these uh activities
actually take place so assume that the
translator was kicked out from this Flow
State and ends up in a hesitation State
here um something very similar could
happen the initialization of these
parameters first and then if you look
back into this part of the process here
the IDE the assumption is that the that
something the translator has a feeling
that something is wrong with L normas
with this part of the
translation U and therefore looks very
often back and maybe thinks about how to
go on with this do some remedy and then
goes on so how could that be uh
represented I
think um or maybe it is um it could be
um so during this phase a translator
would think about all kinds of
adjustments of uh the model so it could
imply the adjustment of the transitions
so maybe a completely different uh trans
translation would be chosen so adjust
the translation and then accordingly
adjust the actions what to do next and
accordingly change also beliefs what the
translator will observe when uh changing
all these parameters here so we could
plug this into this overall model again
and we can see that we have here these
two kinds of uh levels one State uh
level and one Action level and uh
switching back and forth between these
two two St or better say a concurrent
activation of these two two
levels of um of Activation so to sum up
this part of my talk here is uh the idea
of the three
states so we have an orientation phase
where a translator takes in new
information um that is an epistemic
affordance basically adjusts uh internal
model checks whether every all the
resources are available to go on to
start with a translation then we have
this fluent production which which is a
flow ST which is a PR pragmatic
affordance where the actual work is done
so here we have a fluent typing um where
um the observations where the where the
production the the actions that take
place are in line with future obser
ation so there these uh these actions
here do not produce his um surprise or
something like this and then we have
this third state where hesitation where
a translator is kicked out somehow from
this Flow State because something went
wrong and uh then this hurdle needs to
be remedied so something needs to have
be happen in order for uh him or her go
back to um that flow state
okay so this is basically uh the idea so
far um and um and we have now um tried
in a small experiment to uh initialize
these parameters in this parti
observable Mark of decision process so I
would like to talk about this part of um
the process where we have an
initialization of the translation
equivalence the alignment groups here
right in this uh reading uh in this
reading and then uh these ABCD matrices
are uh initialized I would like to talk
about this how this could be done and
then in particular also look into this
uh place here where we use this e
parameter to supervise to indicate
whether everything goes wrong uh
According to some habits and
goals okay okay so first if a translator
uh uh allocates these resources we see
something like this we can see something
like this assume that we have a
situation where um the person translates
from English into Spanish so we have
here an English
sentence translated into and this is
happening in the mind so the translator
allocates some kind of resources and has
an idea to translate this sentence into
this Spanish one and we can see here
that we have alignment
groups one to uh eight in this case but
they ordered already in the order of the
target language syntax you can see here
these three first words are quite
monotonous translation but then there is
some kind of reordering here in the end
but the translator mentally
reorders uh these alignment groups into
the Spanish order and allocates somehow
this marov uh process here so this is
would be perhaps the first step and then
uh U we have in this model here a kind
of a prior so this D1 is the prior what
is the prior of the first uh action to
be taken and this prior would be that
the translator starts with the first
word to translate in their uh allocated
uh chain here okay so all the
probability masses associated with the
first word there is not actually not a
choice to start somewhere else of course
that could be different if they break up
somewhere in the middle then this
probability Mass would be somewhere else
but right in the beginning all the
probability would be onward zero next we
have the initialization of this
preferences and here um is let's if we
assume that the segment has eight words
so 0 to7 here then the pref difference
is that the translator goes through the
segment from the first word to the last
word where the last word has the highest
probability so this kind of probability
distribution would um would prefer the
ordering going through uh through the
the the graph in the order of the
alignment
groups then we can we initi the
initialization of the transition
matrices the B matrices could look like
this so for the moment we have in this
uh Toy implementation uh three kinds of
actions we have insertions a translator
can insert something delete something or
read three kinds of actions so we have
three kinds of different transitions
from one state from one AC alignment
group to the next one and here um in
when inserting the translator would like
to go from one state to the next from
one alignment group to the next
alignment group here so means that for
instance they are in alignment group two
after the insertion they would find
themselves in alignment group three but
it could be also the case that um the
writing process the word is long for
instance or the translator only writes a
small part of the word that after a
writing event after a typing after an
insertion the translator still finds
itself in alignment group two because
they didn't finish it so some
probability mass is still uh left over
for this possibility here or it could be
that uh that this word was very short or
maybe it was a very strong collocation
and the translator wrote in one go more
than one word and they could find
themselves after uh typing in alignment
group translation for alignment group
two they could find themselves in
alignment group four here so there's
some probability Mass left over
distributed for different kinds of
possibilities something very analogous
here with the deletions when deleting
the translator would go backwards now
from alignment group four for instance
to alignment group three but it could
also be that there's a half a word
deleted or that there's a couple of
words deleted so there's a probability
that the translator will be end up in a
different alignment group so they can
cycle around the same alignment group or
they can jump over one and so on and if
reading something nothing happens in the
output so they would stay in the same
alignment group but there's also
probability that actually they will find
themselves in a different kinds of an
alignment group and this can be the case
for instance um when here this
likelihood of recognition is the a
initialization of this a parameter so
that is the probability of the
observation being in an a certain
alignment group given they are in a
certain State here so assume the
translator is in alignment group one
they could it could well be that they
have input and they observe that
actually already word number three is
produced or something else so that would
be this probability but the highest
probability would be according to this
initialization that the the observation
is that they would always see uh observe
there are
in a state which they are actually in
right but it could be differently too
okay so that would be the initialization
of ab c d matrices and now I would like
to talk a little
bit uh about this e Matrix and we have
used this I don't know whether this was
intended to be uh so in uh this
architecture um we have used this e
parameter to indicate whether a
translator should perhaps uh jump out of
leave this Flow State and go into
another state and uh in the following
way so so so the idea would be that if
something here the uh the the future is
planned right so the the translator
thinks what is the best possible path to
pursue in the future and if there is no
clear uh distinction if there there's no
clear idea what happened in the past or
in the future there would be some
confusion some kind of high entropy
perhaps and this would indicate that
maybe something goes wrong and the
translator would leave that flow State
and go into another state and uh we
tried uh I tried several ways of how
that could be uh kind of computed and
one way would be to look into the past
so we are assume we are in uh in this
alignment group group two here and this
Pi would then predict what the next uh
uh State and the next alignment group is
here and it would take into account the
past the the what was already produced
and we so we have the past the alignment
uh activity unit one and two with their
respective States and from this past
observation they would predict what is
the next state what is the next state
the top level state here and and it
turned out that this doesn't work very
well so this probability distribution
just gives us by chance distributions
but if we take into account also the
future so means what is anticipated how
this path continues with activity unit
three and four in the future then uh
this uh gives us a a probability above
chance whether a translator should stay
in this Flow State or go out and do
something else okay and that's basically
what I uh would like to say I just
thought this is very surprising uh these
uh uh that the that the future actually
the anticipated future helps u a
translator to decide whether they should
U move from a flow State into a
hesitation in this case okay to my
conclusion would be like this so this is
a very preliminary implementation and
then uh the idea would be that we
actually would need to implement still a
layer one uh zero where the actual
insertions and deletion takes place um
um so this has not been done or only
very roughly I didn't present this then
we would need an evaluation So
eventually we have uh this large
database more than 5,000 actually more
than 6,000 sessions and we could train
all these parameters on the different
sessions and we have um and then we
would need an
evaluation um method somehow to evaluate
the output of this agent and to see
whether they can simulate um the real
data to what extent they can simulate
this real data that we
have um then we have also a fine grained
that's what we are trying to work on
right now a finer grained classif a of a
hesitation a hesitation could be due as
we have seen in this particular um
instantiation that the translator
rereads the target language Target uh
word very many times but we also have
instances where the translator goes back
and forth from the source to the Target
side Compares obviously something or
where they where they reread pieces of
text and so on and all these different
kinds of patterns would indicate
different cognitive activity
and maybe they could um give some
indication what leads to the hesitation
what happens there and how to model this
in more fine Grant then eventually if we
have an evaluation method then we could
uh also Implement some learning so we
can learn all these ABCD matrices uh
dependent on translation Styles
expertise and text difficulties for
instance so in this database we not only
have the data but we also have metadata
so we have for
instance uh information about expertise
who was it who produced this translation
so we have we could model expertise and
we would assume that trans or we already
know that expert translators produce
translations in different ways than
novice translators do then we have
different translation Styles right in
the beginning uh I showed two Styles we
have this planner who carefully reads
first uh the text and then and then
starts typing or we have this head stter
different translation Styles and we
could see how we could modify this ABCD
matrices in order to Mo model these
different translation Styles then we
have this planning Horizon this pie so
how much in the future does a translator
look and uh and what are the effects how
for instance does linguistic structure
play a role there's there's some kind of
controversy in the in the in the
translation Community as to whether
translators take in full uh linguistic
phrases or whether they only look into
some words ahead and uh to what extent
so the linguistic structure plays a role
in planning the Horizon and then of
course we have this whole other work
package to annotate the data so as as of
now we have six texts
annotated um but we can also do this
this is all the six texts are for
English into Spanish and we have very
many different languages we have also
different translation modes we are also
considering to look into post editing
right now how does this whole idea uh
scale over to post editing modes um and
there are certainly many more ways to uh
analyze the agent in future and that's
my uh my conclusion and my end thank you
very much for listening and if you have
some comments or questions please go
ahead thank you Michael that was awesome
that was really cool and it's cool to
see how it's developed
from many times talking with you about
it in the textbook group so to kick off
the discussion how about morit Andor
Fabio please feel free to say hello
introduce yourself and give any opening
remarks or thoughts
thoughts whichever one of you want to go
first hi can I start please all right
then so okay so hello Michael Daniel and
everyone watching
us uh well you know Mich also I work
with um translation process data you
mentioned some of the work I did on
micro macr translation units but what I
was really curious to discuss with you
is just this final idea that you talk
about planning Horizons right so and in
your example I mean from a human
perspective right not from the kind of
implementation that you're proposing
here but how we could just see one thing
in relation to the other so um people
usually talk about you you talked about
linguistic structure for the planning
Horizon thing right people usually talk
about function and content Words which
is perhaps kind of of easier for people
to understand but in the work I do and
then you and mor have already taken up
on it so we talk
about conceptual encodings and
procedural encodings and hybrid
encodings so in terms of inferential
processing oh um conceptual encoding
would constrain inational processing and
an example you gave there was just like
Las normas traditional is the
traditional Norms to what extent
syntactic priming you know so
in a way guides this kind of planning
Horizon in there the
other thing would be conceptual
encodings these expand infuential
processing to a sense that they can be
enriched and me just like you could say
instead of for normas Les normas Trad
traditional you could have guidelines or
rules or instructions so this would be
open it right so uh to what extent the
this idea of conceptual and procedural
encodings constraining or expanding
inferential processing would have an
impa an effect or an impact on the
planning Horizon that you propose at the
end is that something that you have
taken into consideration or is it
something that one should take into
consideration as far as the work was
implementing your propos is concerned so
that is for
me yeah C certainly so I would assume
that this function words go along with a
whole frame maybe uh they're not
standing alone but they modify a frame
so yes so we didn't really um uh we
didn't really look into this so the all
this we I mean we're um a little I mean
quite ahead so this is something for the
future but I think uh yes your idea is a
good idea to see uh to what extent and
function word and content word would
change the Horizon and I would assume if
there's a function word that would uh
imply their Horizon would be further
right so there is this some ideas from
this construction grammar that a whole
frame must be available before a
translator can actually produce a
translation so they must have a a whole
frame whatever that is whether it's a
noun phrase or clause or sentence or so
that must be available before a
translator can uh produce a translation
so I was thinking in this line um but of
course this also implies your idea with
function words and content words right
um they are somehow encoded in these
frames um yeah so so this would be maybe
one idea one could look one could see to
what extent these Horizon requires
complete linguistic structures or maybe
only part partial so we talking here
about the source uh segment right the
source
segment um but yeah I I guess there's
much that one can do and experiment with
uh and see also the interaction of this
Horizon with the other kinds of
initializations how does this interact I
I believe there's much interesting stuff
to test when this agent Works a little
bit better as it does right now yeah
most certainly I would be interested in
following it up because I think there is
kind of very interesting thing in there
for us to look at yeah
okay yeah um yes um so I think it was
2011 that I saw my ever first first ever
progression graph in in Copenhagen and
it was like seeing the light and
suddenly sort of there was there was a
possibility of of um yeah working with
uh a kind of data that wasn't available
before then so I think um the the
database which back then wasn't a
database of course it it was just
scattered experiments and and so on so
it has come a long way and I think
that's great and soon we'll have an
agent possibly um so so yeah I hope so
yes exactly so
so I have one comprehension question and
um I your slides weren't numbered but
but uh where you essentially map uh your
your the data onto the free energy
principle uh situating the translator as
an agent in in this equation right um
The Source text reading uh um takes the
place of uh perception
right yes yes yes and maybe I'm I'm I'm
naive in that sense but but um but
reading um or or generally comprehension
of of linguistic material there's quite
a bit of evidence that comprehension
engages the very same production
mechanisms that are at play
during yes during during language
production so I've always found it
difficult theoretically or empirically
indeed uh to separate uh Source text
reading processes from Target text
production processes but obviously right
typing is typing and reading is reading
but still um the kinds of processes that
take place while reading the source text
I mean we have core activation that is a
reality um it's it's I guess Beyond
doubt that uh target language aspects
play a role during Source text reading
and and in on several slides in your
talk um you've intimated this um this
quite close link between the two
processes
so how how how do you deal with that in
in in in this agent or in in this
framework yeah so they're separating out
into these two
factors this is only one possibility how
this free energy could be reduced so uh
but both kinds of Parts contribute to
this reduction
and um so uh yeah so there is some kind
of
anticipation uh in the reading that's I
guess what you're saying no so you you
read something that you want to read to
reduce that free energy and I think
that's U that's implied here in this um
evidence I'm yeah so I'm not really U
very sure what your question is um but
the idea would be that we have these two
kinds of
possibilities it could be factored
differently uh or
uh um formalized differently um but
basically they are two these two
possibilities either you change the
world to make it more closely to your
preferences or you change your internal
model to make it come closer to what uh
you can observe so so how the external
world or the observations present
themselves of course there is a kind of
a dependency between these two so
there's a predictive uh
processing um I I guess that's what
you're talking about right predictive
exactly so so I mean also in your
Publications you talk about adapting the
world as uh producing a certain Target
text or adapting the target text once
it's written and so on right but but
that very same principle I think can
apply to the source text reading process
right I mean I I I don't think it's a
problem for this model or anything I I
just I just wonder how how how you would
um translate that into your in your
implementation if if I'm correct the
action part of uh of of your model is
the actual typing right but if reading
is an action then might change how you
implement the whole thing or not maybe I
misunder could I give a thought on that
please yes yeah well there have been
many active inference models of
reading and in those settings the action
the affordances are the icate and so
there's icting across this is even finer
scale than the progression graphs that
were shown here to differentiate letters
to reduce uncertainty about words
differentiation of words within a
sentence and and so on within a broader
narrative context so that's the kind of
action as ocular motor movement and then
the hidden State the external World
state is like the semantic position of
the sentence and then on the outbound
from the agents the actions could
include
typing and so one could either abstract
or coar grain away and just say we're
just going to accept the words as
observations or you can go finer scale
with the actions being the ocular motor
secting which might be important in the
case of like
dyslexia or can just accept the word
straightforwardly as an
observation and then it's really
interesting to think about what is the
task of
translation in that setting and how do
the language models that we have today
help us understand this kind of semantic
transposition from one language to
another which many have written about
and thought about like if there's a a
street called Main Street do you
translate it as Main Street or do you
change main but leave Street or do you
leave one but not the other so there's a
lot of degrees of freedom in the
understanding of the task but you're
absolutely right that every um model and
active inference you have a kind of
inbound observ like modality an outbound
action selection approach and then for
hierarchical metacognitive models there
can be
action that is internal like
attention so then those don't need to be
overt activity like typing or eye
movement yeah so so I that go ahead Mo
so in that sense um in these models I
guess reading a text uh is is is
understood in the terms of generating
that text really
right the icade could be understood as
not seeking out necessarily the most
rewarding section of text but reducing
uncertainty and so the agent has some
generative model of text a deeper
structure of language or even the deeper
structure of of the world their core
knowledge priors and then their activity
is
selected to reduce their uncertainty
about the
text and so their generative model is is
kind of reconstructing the semantics of
the text as they sort of it's like
picking up an unknown object and just
touching it to familiarize oneself with
the semantic shape in this
case and that's a generative active
process it it very sounds to me like a
like a Decon constructive process of
reading right I mean s of the the text
is not a static entity you you're
actually changing it by reading it and
and so yeah but I'm sorry I interrupted
you
Michael yeah yeah so I I think um this
could happen in what I call this layer
zero so that is not we didn't really
address this right so this would be
something uh still on a lower level um
and um yes so I'm I'm not really sure to
what extent Gaye data should be uh
modeled there and typing so certainly in
this layer zero we have typing
activities but to what extent we also
should model their gaze activities maybe
that's possible to and how they
interfere maybe that could Mo be modeled
inside this layer zero down there
letting basically unaffected the stuff
that I have presented so far but perhaps
it's also like this that if we implement
this and have some ideas it could maybe
affect the other layers so this
architecture could could be open and
stuff can be changed no so I don't know
one would need to try all this but also
our data that we have the granularity
that you
sugest is not really suited so this I
guess if we look into s stes and exact
reading patterns and so on um our data
that we have is is too noisy for those
kinds of modeling I think we have rough
so there's often drift in as you know no
there's often drift in in this gaze data
uh the Gaze to word mapping is not U
always very precise only only
approximately so I'm not really sure um
how these things could be modeled then
in this in this lower level uh layer
zero or so but maybe it could also be
like this if we have a set of data that
is very precise that you have uh
recorded with um with much more
controlled experiments maybe this could
form a kind of this kind of processes
that you allude to and then on top of
this there could be the other uh
processes I don't know but this would be
even a step further yeah I mean there
there is definitely noise in the data
but it's it's certainly less than 50%
noise right I didn't I mean it's
difficult to to assess this it's
difficult
to with um headsets coming into broader
use there may be millions
of eye tracking speech recognition and
production data sets
so articulating the structure and the
kind of adjacencies these models is very
important um also you could model that
noise in the eye tracking assignment as
a kind of sensor noise and so yeah of
course noise is going to um degrade the
quality of inference relative to a
noisess observation but there's still
vastly more information than not um
right I'll ask some questions from the
live chat okay Dave Douglas asks English
default noun phrase word order is
precisely the opposite of that of
Spanish which we saw in the
example uh a naive natural language
processing Theory TR transformational
grammar for example would predict that
translators use a stack in their brains
to push and pop phrase components do
your data see fulfillment of
transformational grammar or does the
stack hypothesis match behavior for
short phrases but break down with longer
phrases well we didn't I mean in this
architecture we don't talk about these
linguistic
theories um but it could be so maybe in
this so that alludes to a little bit the
same question that Fabu had no what is
what what is about the prediction the
the pi what is the Horizon the
prediction Horizon and whether we can
use you know relevance Theory with with
with with function words and with
content words or we use uh construction
Grammar with frames and they these
frames uh should be fulfilled or we use
chumsky uh stuff all this could be tried
I I don't have any reservation with
respect to any of those so all possible
or we could just you know look for
engrams
right
um irrespectively of the
type but yes so that's what we often see
in the data actually that a translator
if there is a reordering like this right
so so assume that inside a a monotonous
kind of a translation there is suddenly
required a reordering of the words into
the target language then we can see that
the translator looks ahead EXA L that
amount of text in the source language
that uh accounts amounts to that
reordering so translator has a very good
feeling for U for this the structure and
for the restructuring and from where to
get the necessary data in the source
text where the eyes need to go to get
the necessary data to continue
translation so this is amazing how
precisely um then translators can look
into this data and pick out this
information that they need in order to
continue that is I mean in experienced
translators I I find
that very
surprising if if if I'm go ahead please
please if I may I I have I have one one
other question about um the how how How
likely it is you think that
um the kind of agent you you will
hopefully soon produce generalizes to
other tasks other than translation ah
Dan brought this in into into mind but I
mean you know sort of the task of
translation I mean there's yakobson the
very old sort of quote from yakobson
right s of not not antl yakobson but
Roman yakob right I mean sort of you
know is is comprehending the world an
act of translation I mean you know that
General but but what other task can you
see in application of this agent and the
principles that govern it well I'm first
of all busy with trying to understand
the situation right now and applying it
to our
data um yeah so I don't know well I I
mean basically all kinds of text
production first of all but uh I don't
know so we are talking about linguistic
uh events here I
guess
yeah cing C coding or ah I I was not
thinking of
this that is yeah well it was a question
from the live chat from upcycle Club
wrote I also have a question would it be
possible to extend or modify this model
to cover
transcription so transcription where
there's an auditory modality
so different
sensory input at the at the kind of
embodied layer of the model but after it
propagates into a semantic
layer there might be something like a
more General linguistic Nexus where
whether it came in through through the
auditory sense or the visual sense and
then whether it was going out through
typing or through speaking
there might be some shared skills or it
may be a hypothesis to test that where
where do these different language
skills
um relate to each other one model would
be there's a single linguistic Nexus
sensory input independent sensory or
action output
independent another extreme hypothesis
would be that there are totally
different or very
different cognitive architectures that
are
apt for these different linguistic
tasks no well we actually have spoken uh
data in our database and the way we have
done this is so there is a speech a
spoken signal and we have uh assigned a
Tim stamp for every word so we have a
transcription of the spoken signal into
text and then assigned a Tim stamp for
each word and then it really doesn't
matter in this database it it just looks
like uh typed translation right so
because there's a time stamp and there's
a word you know a sequence of characters
and whether that was initially typed by
the translator or spoken doesn't matter
so we know of course in the analysis and
the analysis is different and there's a
couple of papers also that we have uh
with with with the spoken data only
recently uh one paper where we have a a
site translation with text site
interpretation with text a quite
complicated
setup so it's it's possible and uh well
I guess that's the Assumption somehow
similar processes take place in the mind
um of a translator when whether they use
this mode or that mode um well maybe not
maybe different but in the database at
least it it looks the same and I don't
see Pro a problem to model this uh in a
way but then also this architecture is
not meant as actually a translation
system so this is not a replacement of a
machine translation system it's not
meant to be like this it's rather meant
to assess the effort so what is the
process of the um of the translation so
so it assumes I I mean in this example
that I gave we I assume that there is a
translation available and this agent
would then just um uh reproduce how
effortful it is to produce that
particular translation so where does the
eye go for example where are pauses
where do problems occur where does a
translator get stuck all this but given
that there is already a translation it
would not be a new way of machine
translation but rather autal to this
looking into the process how the
translation comes into being that's what
the agent would model I well at least
that's currently my
idea or both of those orthogonalities
could be embodied in an architecture
that does translation as a cognitive
process and observes its own translation
metacognitively to track its effort or
maybe to improve its learning because
definitely as a language learner English
and
otherwise when you had policy oh just
plan for longer or just it's like but
tell that to a beginner language learner
it's like well I may not have the agency
to Simply plan longer or I might not
have the linguistic affordances to
conjugate this word in this way
yeah so how do you think this kind of
model of of linguistic effort helps us
understand language learning yeah so
there you have it there you have another
application and I can completely see
that fit so how does uh language
beginners
uh learn this now what kinds of
processes go on there how can we model
this in this agent and what uh and what
consists progress in language learning
so what what kinds of parameters change
as a language learner goes from the very
beginning stage to a more advanced stage
how can we model this in the ABCD
matrices also in the look ahead uh
parameters and so on I think that that
could be completely fine example
different from translation uh how this
agent could be used yeah interesting
good ide here who would who would own
the agent own yeah yes so intellectual
property rights yes I mean this is worth
money right I mean who who benefits from
this yeah well it's still long time
ahead but until now all the database was
made available uh free and
openly
and but on a non-commercial basis I
think that's the
license um but first it would need to be
developed but if it's really worth money
so I'm very happy if
you want to buy a
share but this is a very interesting
question and it's it's pragmatic it's
not linguistic conceptual or ontological
but this balance or blend of well what
is open source in the active inference
ecosystem the packages like
pmdp and the analytical framework and
the education and these components are
open source and then how does that work
with what people develop in what ways is
the active inference generative model
development ecosystem similar or
different than say the Linux open-source
development
environment maybe some people do just
want to put things out there with a
Creative Commons or with a with a purely
open or with a
non-commercial open license but these
are major major questions that come up
in in every area of
modeling yeah I think it's it's a big
question and there's no easy answer
right well my my I my impression is uh I
mean it's far uh far away right now from
that situation but there could be an
open version of this agent and then if
some somebody wanted to use that for
special purposes there could be somehow
I guess there are many business models
like this no they rely on open source
stuff and if they uh tune this fine tune
this to special applications then the
kind of business interests come in I I
think there's many ways uh and
many
uh many many templates how to go about
those
things yeah it's an interesting question
Just One Last point on that is there can
be an open-source generative model that
uses proprietary data so then you can
say this is how the iades work this is
how the attention mechanism works but
also we have this curated data set that
is our product on the other hand there
could be an open source data set and
someone could say we have a generative
model that's our proprietary work or
there's the quadrant with both being
proprietary or both being open but
that's just one way to kind of slice up
the space and people who have academic
backgrounds or other might prefer or
dwell in one of those
areas I'll read another comment from the
live chat and see if any of you fellows
have a thought so Dave
writes this will be a hard one to read
speed pitch and volume within individual
spoke words in addition to pauses are
critical to know what what exactly is
being
said how do we model
these features of speech and
language that on one hand language
models are showing us well you get a ton
of semantics out of just the string of
tokens and yet
this abrades away the
pauses and the tonality and these
features that in terms of our
recognition and generation of speech can
be almost dominant
factors yeah so if you want me
to say something with respect to
this I guess well if you transcribe this
manually this the the speech um there is
aan that could be used and one could add
those kinds of additional ations in
another track for instance intonation or
speed uh yeah I don't know whether there
is tools to figure this automatically so
usually speech recognition uh systems
only have the transcription of the words
but not additional information for our
experiments that we transcribed we used
Watson IBM system that speech
recognition system was the only one that
we found that produces a time stamp for
each word that was produced and that was
very interesting because we could then
compute um the time when a word was
spoken and heard so we could compute an
ear voice span with this kind of
information but they would not produce
this kind of additional protic prootic
information or something like this so
from of course from the time stamp you
can see the speed right uh that would be
somehow an implicit encoding I guess
um but uh the pitch and all this uh
there is no such information I don't
know whether there is speech recognition
systems that produce this kind of things
but once this is there it's just an
additional feature for a word and it
could be taken into account just like
any other uh
super segmental feature perhaps like
like for instance a phrase take or
something like
this
and it could then be also compared with
linguistic structure and the prootic
structure and so on all these nice
things could be done if this features
are there I don't see a problem I mean
from that point of view I don't see a
problem how that could be or that it
could be tackled in this approach I see
a problem more of from where do we get
this data and whether we have tools to
produce this automatically or
semi-automatically
maybe interesting yeah Dave writes in
the chat assembly AI also captures word
onset and termination to millisecond
granularity so that's what we use for
the active inference Journal like when
we transcribe and curate this guest
stream or any of our streams we have
that kind of timing data and then um
it's kind of like reading between the
lines we could then add another track
like pitch deviation or volume
deviation and then do some kind of aect
inference okay what if we only saw the
volume deviance or if we only saw the
the pacing
patterning and then okay now what if we
have this kind of Sensor Fusion with the
tokens and then these prootic elements
of speech and then do model
comparison and as you point out this is
this isn't trying to reconstruct a
translator
in order to make a
translation
algorithm but it can give us some
diagnostic information on the
translation on the effort
yeah um Fabio or morit any kind of other
thoughts or or
questions so where where does the
research go or how can people get
involved if they're curious these
topics so I I think um we have now uh
well I outlined in the beginning a
trajectory of this translation process
research and I think this uh agent is
really a new way of modeling this and I
I see much potential there to actually
model this so so we looked into we an we
we analyzed the translation process data
that we have for many years and I think
the type time is ripe now also with all
your fantastic Institute and the
activities that go on in this institute
I mean that fits somehow I think it's a
timely kind of a thing so that's I think
that's where the research goes I mean at
least from my side and anyone who is
interested in joining in very welcome so
there are so many open
ends um that could be put together uh
I've tried to outline a few ideas that I
was thinking about and of course the
code that um is there can be made
available um to anyone who would like to
continue
there uh yeah Bobo or morit where do you
go from
here well I'm I'm interested in that
level zero I am uh I I like I like the
small things and and and I I I think
they are
um promising I find them interesting and
and and um yeah so I hope I hope to
contribute on that
level thank you
excellent whereas for me I mean I've
always been interested in human
influential processing and the the
question of the planning Horizon and the
tie in there is what really attracts me
at the moment so to see what the
relationship would be between you know
so um the planning horizon or
implementing that in the model that
would somehow emulate things we know
about human inferential
processing yeah awesome a closing note
from Dave this is the kind of high
volume highly granular data needed to
scrutinize and improve the active
inference in free energy principal
Frameworks expert Behavior especially is
really valuable to study cool well thank
you all thank you Michael for this great
presentation and work till next time
thank you so much for having us thank
you thank you bye bye
bye